<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the lord mayor, and the Court of Aldermen, at the Guild-Hall Chappel on November the 23d. 1684 by Thomas Wagstaffe ...</title>
            <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34696</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14563216</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14563216</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102605</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66000)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102605)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1078:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the lord mayor, and the Court of Aldermen, at the Guild-Hall Chappel on November the 23d. 1684 by Thomas Wagstaffe ...</title>
                  <author>Wagstaffe, Thomas, 1645-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, VIII, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:102605:1"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Smith Mayor,</signed>
               <date>Martis <hi>xxv<hi rend="sup">to</hi>
                  </hi> die Novembris <hi>1684.</hi> Annoque Regni Regis <hi>Caroli</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundi, Angl. <hi>&amp;c. xxxvi,</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Mr <hi>Wagſtaffe</hi> to Print his Sermon preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Mayor and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel, on <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> Morning laſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102605:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED Before the Right Honourable THE Lord Mayor, AND THE <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT</hi> of <hi>ALDERMEN,</hi> AT THE <hi>Guild-Hall Chappel</hi> On <hi>November</hi> the <hi>23d.</hi> 1684. By <hi>THOMAS WAGSTAFFE,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the Biſhops Head in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102605:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102605:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir <hi>JAMES SMITH,</hi> Kt. Lord Mayor Of the CITY of LONDON, And to the Honourable the COURT of ALDERMEN.</head>
            <p>THE Ends I aim'd at in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe were, to do the Church right, to take off unreaſonable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices, and to perſwade Men to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the beſt eſtabliſhed Church in the World. And the ſame (I humbly preſume) were intended by your Order for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing it: I do not apologize for the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:102605:3"/>(though I am conſcious of it) yuor Commands warrant its Publication; and Obedience is part of the Religion of every Member of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I therefore only add my Prayers, that God would bleſs all Endeavours that tend to the undeceiving the People, and ſettling them in <hi>Unity, Peace</hi> and <hi>Loyalty;</hi> not only for your Lordſhip and the Honourable Court (whoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakings in this kind are very remarkable) but alſo for every good Man in the Nation.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obedient and Humble Servant,</hi> Tho. Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102605:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. COR. 8.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>When ye Sin ſo againſt the Brethren, and offend their Weak Conſcience, ye Sin againſt Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMONG other the Reproaches laid upon the Church of <hi>England</hi> by its Adverſaries, one is that its Impoſitions are of a Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Nature, that it injoyns ſuch things, as are offnſieve to Weak Brethren, and the very Words I have read to you are (tho ignorantly) yet petulantly enough applyed to Charge the Church with Sin againſt Chriſt, in offending the Weak Conſciences of the Brethren of the Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as if the impoſing two or three Ceremonies, were as Injurious to tender minds now, as eating of Meat Sacrificed to <hi>Idols</hi> in the beginning of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</p>
            <p>A Charge it is of a very high Nature, for ſeeing the power the Church is inveſted with, is for Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, not Deſtruction: ſeeing it ought to have all Tenderneſs, and compaſſionate regards towards the little Ones in Chriſt, if (inſtead of this) ſhe only lays ſtumbling Blocks in their way; the Church
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102605:4"/>would be (what her Enemies have called her) an Adulterous Spouſe of Chriſt, and which btrayes the truſt her Lord hath repoſed in her, of forwarding the Salvation of all Men under her Care: But if thoſe bethe Repreſentations only of Ignorance, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, if in truth (upon full Conſideration) there appears no juſt Ground for ſuch a Charge. It will not (I conceive) be unbecoming the filial Piety of a true Son, to vindicate the Innocence of his Mother, to wipe of thoſe Aſpertions which have been caſt upon her, either by the Ignorant, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, or by the crafty and malicious. In order to this purpoſe, I ſhall indeavour to do theſe things fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> To ſtate the Notion or Nature of Scandal or Offence, as it is repreſented to us in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</item>
               <item>2. To inquire whether thoſe that urge this againſt us, are really offended in a Goſpel Senſe, tho the things in controverſie ſhould be as evil as they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them.</item>
               <item>3. Suppſe they were offended, yet theſe 2. things ought to be conſidered.</item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Firſt.</hi> That this cannot with any Senſe or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be urged by them that are offended.</item>
                     <item>2. If the Matter of Offence be in things indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, we cannot forbear them upon account of a weak Brother, where our Liberty is already deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</item>
                     <item>3. Tho they are not offended by us, they are really offended by the Leaders of the Separation.</item>
                     <item>4. The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath given no Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of offence to any.</item>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102605:4"/>
                     <item>5. Briefly apply this to our ſelves.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I ſhall indeavour to ſtate the Notion of Nature of Scandal as it is repreſented in the Goſpel, and in doing this I ſhall indeavour to conſider the moſt important Caſes mentioned in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: (from whence only we can have it) and from thence frame ſuch a Notion as is agreeable to that Repreſentation the Goſpel makes of it.</p>
            <p>There are two Caſes largely ſpoken to by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the Epiſtles, one is the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Chapters to the <hi>Romans,</hi> the other is the Eighth and Tenth Chapters of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> Both theſe I ſhall briefly conſider.</p>
            <p>Of that in the Fourteenth and Fifteenth to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> the ſumm (I conceive) is this; among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Chriſtians, there were ſeveral <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Converts; who had not yet worn out the ſence of <hi>Moſes's</hi> Law but thought themſelves, and all others alſo convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Chriſtianity (in ſome meaſure) under the bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of it, as to the Obſervation of Days, Meats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Gentile Chriſtians on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, eſteem'd themſelves free from all ſuch Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that theſe were on parts of the Goſpel diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that therefore neither they nor the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves ought to have any regard or account for them; and this (as it uſually happens in the differences of Parties and Opinions) made them Contemn and Cenſure each other, the Strong deſpiſing the Weak, as too nice and ſuperſtitious, and the Weak judging the Strong as prophane, and neglecters of Gods Law. And this was grown ſo high, that ſome of the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſort were hereby endangered; and there were fears, the <hi>Jews</hi> might be diſcourag'd from Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102605:5"/>by unſeaſonablly exploding thoſe things, which they knew were of divine Inſtitution; and which (tho abrogated) they had yet a Conſcience for. In this Caſe the Apoſtle adviſeth not to <hi>Judge one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but Judge this rather, that no man put a Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Block, or an occaſion to fall in his Brothers way</hi> (Ver. 13.) the prejudices of Education and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms (eſpecially thoſe that had ſuch a Sanction as thoſe of the <hi>Jews</hi>) would not be ſo ſoon worn out; and the ſevere inſiſting upon, or (which is worſe) the reproachfully and contemptuouſly inveighing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, would rather avert and hinder new proſelytes (eſpecially thoſe of ſcrupulous and doubting minds) then any way engage them to another Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, or way of Religion. The <hi>Jews</hi> had been Born, and Bred up under the Rites of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and this was part of their Religion: And ſo ſoon as they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Chriſtianity, preſently to fall foul upon <hi>them,</hi> or to treat them diſdainfully and haughtily for uſing <hi>them;</hi> would be the readieſt courſe to drive them away. And therefore, too the thing be never ſo true, tho they were never ſo much convinc'd that the diſtinction of Days and Meats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away by Chriſt, yet this ought to be mildly and meekly (at leaſt) preſs'd in reference to thoſe who had other perſwaſions concerning them, and who had not ſufficient growth in Chriſtianity, as to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtructed in the Nature and force of Chriſtian Liberty. <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and am perſwaded by the Lord</hi> Jeſus <hi>that there is nothing unclean of it ſelf, but to him that eſteemeth any thing unclean, to him it is unclean</hi> (Ver. 14.) altho as to the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I have a free Liberty, and may follow my own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102605:5"/>Sentiments, yet I am to have reſpect, as well to my Brothers weakneſs, as to my own freedom, and (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thinks otherwiſe) if by any indiſcreer or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable uſe of this Liberty, I offend him, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion him, that is not ſo fully perſwaded, to fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the faith, I ought not to make uſe of it. <hi>If thy Brother be grieved with thy Meat, now walkeſt thou not Charitably, Deſtroy not him with thy Meat for whom Chriſt dyed,</hi> (ver. 15.)</p>
            <p>And this I take to be the Summ of this matter, ſo far as it relates to the caſe of Scandal, and of which (for the preſent) I ſhall deſire only to remark this one thing.</p>
            <p>That the means whereby the weak Brethren were really (or likely to be) offended (in the Caſe I have recited) were reproaching and deſpiſing the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the <hi>Jews,</hi> tho they were really abrogated, and Contemning and Slighting the weaker Chriſtians that us'd them.</p>
            <p>From whence we may briefly inferr (for I ſhall make no further uſe of it) that Vilifying and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ceremonies, and them that uſe them, may as equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be an occaſion of ſcandal as impoſing them. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf took ſuch care in this matter, that rather then offend the <hi>Jews</hi> he actually comply'd with a Moſaical Rite, and Circumcis'd <hi>Timothy.</hi> He had (it ſeems) another opinion of Chriſtian Liberty, than the ſtiff men of Separation; they think their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty invaded by Impoſitions, and they ought not to yield to their Governors, becauſe Chriſt hath mad them free, and yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> (by vertue of his Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty) not to offend them he was among, could uſe an abrogated Rite, and ſuch a one as Chriſt did
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102605:6"/>unqueſtionably free us from. But ſome men have an odd and perverſe Notion of things? They think they have Chriſtian Liverty enough to break all the Laws and Injunctions of their Governours, but they are ſtreight lac'd, and can find no Chriſtian Liberty to comply with them, and obedy them, and this is the difference between Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and them, Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Chriſtian Liberty gave him a Latitude, and he could do any thing that was not Sin, for ſomewhat leſs ends then obedience to Magiſtrates; Circumciſion he knew in it ſelf, was neither neceſſary, nor Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, yet he did uſe it for the ſake and ſatisfaction of thoſe people, but our Libertines cry out they ſhall betray their Liberty in doing any thing they do not like, and they will not go a Haires breadth tho it be to obey their Rulers, and to promote the Churches peace. But this only by the way.</p>
            <p>The ſecond place the Apoſtle inſiſts on in reference to the offending our weak Brother, is that from whence the Text is choſen, and it is ſpoken to in the Eighth and Tenth Chapters, of the Firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and the Caſe I take to be this. Some thought it lawful to eat Meat offered to Idols, and the Reaſon they gave for it was, becauſe an Idol is nothing, and ſo could not convey any Stain or Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to the Meat offer'd to it, that which was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could not infect Gods real Creatures: But ſince he appointed them for our uſe, and ſupport, we might freely and indifferently uſe them for theſe ends, whether they were, or were not ſacrificed to Idols; for why ſhould that which was nothing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar a Man of a Right which God had given him? To this St. <hi>Paul</hi> anſwers by granting the Reaſon that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102605:6"/>it's true, an Idol is nothing, and there is no God but one, and therefore as to the things themſelves they might Eat, or not Eat, as they found themſelves diſpoſed: But there were ſome accidental Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, which might make it unlawful, and inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and thoſe were tho not as to the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet in reference to their Brethren. <hi>For ſome with Conſcience of the Idol unio this Hour, eat it as a thing offered unto an Idol,</hi> that is, they take it as conſecrated Meat, and part of the Idol Worſhip, <hi>and their Conſcience being weak is defiled (Ver. 7.)</hi> thoſe that had been newly converted from Idolatry, were not ſo fully weaned from their old Opinions and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes; but they had (as is uſual in all changes) ſome kind of Sence and Apprehenſion towardes their former Modes of Worſhip, and might the ſooner be brought to relapſe; and when they ſaw them that were confirmed, or Eminent Chriſtians doing the ſame things that Idolaters do, they might be perſwaded that Idolatry was not ſo Vain a thing, and they. who had yet ſome kind of Conſcience towards an Idol, might be induced to do the ſame, and ſo be brought back to Idolatry, from which they had but lately eſcaped. <hi>For if any Man ſee thee which haſt Knowledg ſit at Meat in the Idols Temple, ſhall not the Conſcience of him that is weak be</hi> emboldened to eat <hi>theſe things that are offered to Idols,</hi> and by that means, having not the ſame Sence and eſtimate of things, be made a formal Idolator, <hi>and through thy Knowledg ſhall the weak Brother periſh for whom Chriſt dyed?</hi> (<hi>ver.</hi> 10.11.) If therefore the Liberty a knowing Chriſtian hath, be thus perverſely uſed, as to become a ſtumbling block to the Weak, If this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102605:7"/>knowledg of having a power to eat any of Gods Creatures, be not directed by Love and Charity. It is a ſinful abuſing the priviledges Chriſt hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, and inſtead of complying with, is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Violation of his Will; <hi>But when ye ſo Sin againſt the Brethren, and wound their weak Conſcience, ye Sin againſt Chriſt,</hi> (Ver. 12.)</p>
            <p>And this, I conceive, is the ſum, and full im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of this place, and from theſe two places I have mentioned, we may take a full account of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Scandal, from hence are two things remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That a <hi>Weak Brother</hi> (in a Goſpel Senſe) is ſuch one, as has been newly converted to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and who (for want of Time, Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Inſtruction) is not ſufficiently confirm'd in the Principles of it: 'Tis ſuch a one, whoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity as yet hangs looſe; 'tis new, and unſettled, he hath yet ſome kind of Conſcience, and tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of mind to his former Ways, and ſo he is apt to ſtagger, to be carried away by Temptations, and eaſily to be driven back. His Religion is (as it were) pendulous, and any thing turns the Scales. Fair, and gentle, and prudent Behaviour may win him to a further embracing the Faith; but incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, indiſcreet, and uncharitable Methods may run him again into his former Errours, and this was plainly the Caſe of the Weak Perſons in the places I have conſidered, and this I take to be the true Notion of a Weak Brother: and I do not think there is any other Notion of it in the whole Goſpel. And ſuch Perſon as theſe, every good Man will think it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, to treat with all the Gentleneſs, Yielding and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102605:7"/>Complyableneſs poſſible. To ſubmit to their infirmity, and as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, to become every thing to them, that he might ſave them.</p>
            <p>But what is this to thoſe amongſt us? Is there no difference between the Caſe of new Converts and thoſe Born and Bred up in Chriſtianity? Who have ſuck'd in the principles of Religion with their milk, who have always liv'd under the power of it, and have had time and opportunities more then ſufficient, for conviction, information and inſtruction? If ſuch as thoſe will be always Babes, if their Faith be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled ſtill, ſuch weakneſs is not only a great ſhame, but I fear, when all hearts are try'd, will appear not weakneſs but wilfulneſs.</p>
            <p>Beſides, what hath the Caſe of weakneſs to do with thoſe,<note place="margin">Conference at Hampton Court.</note> who as King <hi>James</hi> ſpeakes are <hi>not only Strong, but Head-Strong,</hi> who are obſtinately wedded to Fooliſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable opinions, whom nothing of Lenity can win, nothing of reaſon can ſatisfy; are theſe to be entertain'd with the ſame tenderneſs that belongs to a weak Brother? Weakneſs indeed is but obſtinacy, and ſtiffneſs in error was never thought an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of compaſſion and ſufferance. Our Saviour himſelf, and his Apoſtles, who always condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Weakneſs, yet vigorouſly and Zealouſly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves againſt perverſeneſs, and ſtubbornneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence we ſee that Scandal or offending a Weak Brother, is no leſs then perverting him from Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and therefore we find in all places cited, that when he is offended, he is ſaid to be deſtroy'd and made periſh: This is plainly the meaning of being offended here. And the being hindred from belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102605:8"/>in Chriſt, or being induc'd to forſake that Belief afterwards, is the ſence of moſt (if not all) of the places of the New Teſtament where the words Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal or Offence are named, I ſhall need to inſtance but in two or three. In the <hi>Thirteenth</hi> Chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew</hi> in the Parable of the Sower and the Seed, that is, as our Saviour himſelf interprets it, himſelf, and his Doctrine at <hi>ver. 20, 21.</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth the Seed in Stony places, is he that heareth the Word, and with joy receiveth it, but he hath not Root; for when Tribulation, or Perſecution, cometh becauſe of the Word, by and by he is offended,</hi> that is, by Reaſon of Tribulation, and Perſecution, which follow upon the profeſſion of the Chriſtian Faith he forſakes it. So Saint <hi>Matthew 18th.</hi> Chapter <hi>ver. 6. Whoſoever ſhall offend one of theſe little Ones that believe in me,</hi> that is, ſhall make them leave the Profeſſion, or Practice of my Faith. So when the <hi>Jews</hi> are ſaid to be <hi>offended</hi> at Chriſt, they were through their own miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceptions and prejudices hindred from believing on him; ſo then <hi>being offended</hi> is not ſo light a thing as ſome make of it, 'tis not being angry or diſpleaſed, but ſuch a thing whereby their Religion is endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered, and they are thereby diſcourag'd either from embracing, or continuing in Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Now this is matter of a very high Nature, and it is no Wonder that the Goſpel, which takes ſo much care for the Salvation of all Men, ſhould (as much as may be) indeavour to prevent the loſs of any, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is the Summ of our Religion as to God, ſo alſo to our Brother, and 'tis a duty incombent on all, both upon the account of God, of their Chriſtianity and of their Neighbour, to propagate and ſpread it,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102605:8"/>and to uſe all fair means that others may entertain it, as well as our ſelves. If therefore, by any behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of ours, there is bred a diſlike and averſion, and our Brother falls away from Chriſt, we betray our Saviour, we hinder his deſign and end in coming, and we contradict the Fundamental Principle of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. Theſe are things therefore of the higheſt concernment, and it is no wonder our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and the Apoſtle gives ſuch ſevere Rules and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctions concerning them. The Salvation of a man is of high importance: 'Twas that for which Chriſt died, and his Religion is the way to it. 'Tis no harſh order therefore, <hi>That we ſhould by all means take care, that our Liberty is no a Stumbling Block to them that are Weak,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9.) And the Apoſtle profeſſes for himſelf, that if Meat make his Brother to offend, he will eat none while the World ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. that is, he will do nothing that is in his power to forbear, rather than hazard the loſs of his Brothers Soul, and truly he muſt have mean thoughts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity, and of Mans Salvation, that will not deny himſelf a great many lawful Freedoms rather than his Brothers Salvation ſhall be hazarded, and he be occaſion'd to forſake Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>And this I take to be the true Notion of Scandal as it is ſtated in the Goſpel, and concerning which thoſe Rules, and Directions of not offending our Brother were made. I confeſs there are Scandals of an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Nature, and in which Sence Divines generally handle this Subject, and that is when our Behaviour occaſions our Brother not to forſake the whole, but to break any part of our Religion and fall into Sin, and this to it be true, yet there is a great difference
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102605:9"/>in degree and malignity, the great Scandal is that which is ſo much ſpoken to, and thoſe things and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions (I have mention'd) tho they may alſo in proportion be binding in reference to the leſſer ones, yet I conceive they are chiefly intended, and do pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily relate to the greater; tho they may be Rules for our Behaviour, and are to be ſo with Reſpect to any Sin of our Brother, yet their firſt and chiefeſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect is in reference to his Total deſertion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</p>
            <p>To comprehend the whole therefore, A Weak Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is offended, when by any uncharitable behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, imprudent uſe of liberty, or other means, he is driven away from Chriſtianity, or occaſion'd to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late any part of it; for tho (as I ſaid) the Rules the Goſpel gives of not offending, have the firſt and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt regard, and were mainly (if not only) intended to ſecure ſuch from falling from the Chriſtian Faith, yet by Analogy and Parity of Reaſon they may have Reſpect to prevent likewiſe their falling into any Sin, and here the argument is good from the greater to the leſs; for if it be a Scandal to drive a man from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity in the Whole, 'tis ſo (tho in an inferior de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree) to occaſion him to forſake any Part of it. The Reaſon and Ground of theſe Rules was that thereby Salvation was hazarded, and a Man's Sulvation is in danger (tho not equally nor ſo much) by his falling into Sin, as by this leaving Chriſtian Religion. This is the firſt, the Nature of Scandal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall indeavour to inquire into matter of Fact, whether they that urge this objection are really of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended in a Goſpel ſence, or whether any reaſonable Man can believe ſo, granting that the things are as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102605:9"/>bad as they repreſent them. I ſhall not here enter into Men's Conſciences, to their own Judge they ſtand or fall. But the ground of this inquiry is this, They are always quarrelling at our Ceremonies, always angry at and diſpleas'd with them, and nothing we can do can perſwade them to an approbation of them. Now this (which they take to be their offence) is an undenyable Argument againſt it, and ſo long as they continue in that mind, they are not only not offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but it is impoſſible they ſhould be ſo. For ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there was that real evil in them, which they ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do, or make us believe they think there is; the impoſing them by the Church, or the uſing them our ſelves, what inconvenience ſoever they may bring to us, can never hazard them, who run from them as far as they are able. Let our Ceremonies be as Anti-Chriſtian and Idolatrous as they would have them, what harm is that to thoſe, who will not ſo much as touch them with one of their Fingers? Had theſe People too great an opinion of Ceremonies, were they apt to worſhip and adore them, and ſhould our juſt and decent uſe of them bring them to this, they would indeed be offended, tho we had not given the occaſion: But now to ſcorn and hate them, to vilifie and reproach them, and all that uſe them, and yet cry out they are offended at them, is a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. In the Caſe of Meat offer'd to Idols, the Strong are forbidden to eat, not becauſe the weak Brother is angry, or diſpleas'd with ſo doing, but for fear he ſhould be too well pleas'd with it, that is ſhould like it ſo well as to do it himſelf, and it was not becauſe they had an ill opinion, but too good opinion of an Idol, for as yet they had Conſcience
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102605:10"/>towards the Idol, and might be emboldened to eat it as part of the Idol Worſhip. Their <hi>Weakneſs</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in having too good thoughts of theſe things, and therefore they ſhould be forborn, leſt they ſhould eſteem them yet more, and ſo be confirm'd in, or return'd to Idolatry. And (in this Senſe) if our Brethren were offended, they ſhould then frequent our Aſſemblies, and Idolize our Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and Eſteem them holier than we do our ſelves. But when they revile and clamour againſt them; when they deride and ſcoff at them, if there ſhould be any hurt in them, theſe (of all Men) are not like to be ſpoiled by our Example: tho kneeling at the Sacrament ſhould be Idolatry, and the Surpliſs, and Common-Prayer downright Popery; yet the Chriſtianity of ſuch cannot be endangered by them. For how can they be poluted, and their weak Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences wounded by any thing they will not uſe? Theſe People therefore think they are offended, only becauſe they are angry and vexed, and who can help it? ſuch things will be, ſo long as there are peeviſh, unquiet, and troubleſome Natures in the World; but ſurely they ought not to hinder the Church from injoyning, or us from uſing any thing that is decent and uſeful. Nay, this is ſo far from being a Scandal, or any Inducement for us to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear theſe things, that upon this very account, and for their ſakes, we ought to be more Zealous and Earneſt in them, if by any means we might bring them to ſome Conſcience of theſe things; if our careful diſcharge of our Duty might win upon them, and they ſeeing our good works might be brought to a juſt regard for Authority, and a right
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102605:10"/>eſteem for the Peace and Union of the Church. For thoſe that for matter of Rites can ſeparate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide, have too mean Eſteem of Unity and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and while they ſee us looſe and careleſs in our Duty, it will be apt to confirm them in their Error. The Weakneſs of our Brethren plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in too much ſlighting Decency and Ceremonies, and too little regard for Authority. And an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency, coldneſs, or complying with them will nouriſh their miſtakes, will confirm them in their ill grounded Opinion, and really offend them.</p>
            <p>There is one Objection to this, and that is, That tho they ſhould not be offended in Reference to the uſe of the Ceremonies, becauſe they do not uſe them, yet the Ceremonies being impoſed by the Church, and they having ſuch an Averſion to them, are thereby prejudic'd againſt our Communion, and ſo want the means of Salvation that is amongſt us, and by that means they may, tho not by the other, be offended. This Objection I do not know that it is urged by any of them, nor indeed can it well be by thoſe who think they have purer Ordinances, and purer Ways of Worſhip. But what weight there is in this Objection, and how far the Church in its Impoſitions may have regard to the Prejudices of People, and whether this will relate to the Caſe of our preſent Diſſenters, will be ſpoke to under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Head.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſing they are really offended, yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever theſe two things ought to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That this cannot with any Senſe or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be uſed by them that are offended.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:102605:11"/>
            <p n="2">2. If the matter of Offence be in things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, we cannot forbear them upon the account of a weak Brother, where our Liberty is already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That this cannot with any Sence or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be urged by them that are offended: I know they think they ſay ſomething, when they ſay they are offended, but whatſoever it may be againſt us, to be ſure it is nothing for themſelves: For they do not conſider that to be offended is a Sin, as well as to offend, and the weak Brother that falls is in as much danger, as he that makes him: For a Scandal becomes a Sin, no otherwiſe, than as it hath Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to other Mens Sins, and if it be a Sin in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Occaſion, 'tis certainly ſo in the immediate Actor. He that cauſes a man to forſake his Duty, (which is the Goſpel Scandal.) is guilty of, and puniſhable for the Scandal, and he that does it, is guilty of, and puniſhable for the Tranſgreſſion of Gods Law: In ſhort, if it be a Sin to entice, to temper, or to provoke to Sin, 'tis certainly not leſs to act, and to perform it, and therefore we read in the Scandals the Goſpel ſpeaks of; Theſe that were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended were not ſo very Innocent, nor in a very hopeful Condition. But they are ſaid to be loſt, to periſh, and to be deſtroyed. And now is not this a hopeful Argument? and can any man uſe it that is really offended? all that he ſays muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound upon himſelf, and every clamour againſt us flies in his own Face; for it is certainly a Duty not to be ſcandaliz'd, as well as not to ſcandal; and if they are offended, and are ſenſible of it, they Sin knowingly; and if they know it, why do they not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102605:11"/>remove their Offences, and forbare to Sin? For 'tis certainly a very ſtrange thing, for Men perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to cry out, They are in a fault, and yet never take care to mend it. But the truth is, the Men that talk at this rate, do not know what they ſay, they take their own unreaſonable Frets, and Diſcontents for Offence, which notwithſtanding in the Goſpel-Senſe is quite contrary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Matter of Offence be in things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in their Nature, where our Liberty is already determined, we cannot forhare them, tho our weak Brother ſhould thereby be offended. And this is our Caſe, the things in Controverſie we believe to be of an indifferent Nature, and ſuch as are in our Superiours Power to impoſe, and when lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority hath interpoſed, we are no longer free, and the things which are indifferent in their Nature, are not now indifferent in their uſe, we are under the binding Power of the Law, and are obliged to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them, by Virtue of thoſe Injunctions which command us to ſubmit our ſelves to the Powers ſet over us: And now (in this Caſe) what would they have us to do? would they have us deſpiſe Authority, and break thro the Laws? this perhaps might pleaſe and ſatisfie them; but ſure they do not expect we ſhould wound our own Conſciences to heal theirs, that we ſhould Sin our ſelves to prevent Sin in them. For (if they do not,) we do believe we are bound in Conſcience to obey our Governours in all things Lawful: the things that occaſion'd the Scandals the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, were as yet left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determin'd, and they might as well omit, as uſe them. But 'tis not ſo with us, we are tyed up by Laws, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102605:12"/>therefore if our Brethren ſhould be offended, we may be ſorry, but we cannot help it: We may wiſh they were more Judicious and Underſtanding, than to be ſcandaliz'd at Innocent Rites, and we may take all the Care we can to inform them better; but we muſt not therefore forbear them, and diſobey our Rulers; we may have all Tenderneſs and Charity for them. But Charity begins at home: we cannot out of Love to them ruin our ſelves, and neglect our Duty, and make other Mens miſtakes the Rule of our Conſciences. And this is the third Thing,</p>
            <p n="4">4. I ſhall indeavour to make out, that tho they are not offended by us, yet they are really offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Leaders of the Separation. And this will retort the Argument upon themſelves: For this purpoſe I ſhall need only to remind you, That the formal Nature of Scandal is ſuch a Behaviour of ours, as whereby our Brother is lead into Sin. And to make this good againſt the Heads of the Separation I ſhall premiſe, and take for granted theſe three Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Obedience to Governours in all Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Things is a Duty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Separation from a Lawful Communion, from a Church whereof we are National Members, and wherein we may Communicate without Sin, is a Sin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſuch a Church. Theſe three (which might eaſily be made out) but would take up too much time for the preſent Diſcourſe, and which I muſt now therefore take for granted. But they being granted it will follow, that thoſe Perſons, who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102605:12"/>entice them from their Obedience, and who lead them into Schiſm, are the perſons that really offend them, (<hi>i.e.</hi>) theſe are the Men that Occaſion them to Sin. Thoſe therefore that lead them into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, and teach them to deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities, thoſe that make them believe two or three Ceremonies are as heavy as the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaical Yoke, that by calling hard Names, as <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, fright and ſcare poor Poeple from our Communion; theſe are they that offend them, that is, who make them Sin, and pervert them from their Duty. Where therefore they learn to be proud and untractable, to be Factious and Schiſmatical, to be Seditious and Ungovernable, there it is they muſt lay their Offence. And if it be ſeriouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into, whence it is that theſe Men have taken ſuch an ill and Unrighteous Opinion concerning us, and the things we uſe, as to believe the Communicating with us will pollute and defile them, this cannot be in the things themſelves, and 'tis ſome what odd, that Men ſhould believe the Church of <hi>England</hi> is Popiſhly given, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding is, (and any man may know it that will) the chiefeſt ſupport of Proteſtaniſm, and the greateſt Bulwark againſt Popery in the World; 'tis ſtrange that Men in their wits ſhould think, that whining and ſighing, that undigeſted thoughts, and crude, (not to ſay nonſenſical) Expreſſions, ſhould be the Spirit of Prayer, and more fit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Neceſſities of a Congregation, than theſe that have been deliberately pen'd by the moſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious and Godly in a Nation: I ſay, whence is it, that Men take up ſuch Unrighteous Eſtimates? there
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102605:13"/>is not one of a thouſand of them that ever examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the truth of things, or have any thing to ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſome ſcurrilous Expreſſions; they take them upon truſt, and ſwallow down every thing their Leaders dictate, and ſo they become offended, and ſeperate from us, and fly from our Communion, And ſo long as they are made to believe, that when we kneel at the receiving the Communion, we are Idolaters, that the Croſs in Baptiſm is making new Sacraments, that when they Communicate with us, they ſhall joyn themſelves to a Company of <hi>Jews, Heathens,</hi> or <hi>Papiſts;</hi> theſe Men indeed are offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but wo be to them by whom ſuch Offences come, who raiſe up Bug-bears, and ſcare-Crows, and drive Chriſtian People from what they are bound in Conſcience to do; theſe therefore that make them divide and ſeparate, that are always rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at an Innocent Church, that feed their preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, and what their Diſcontents, that inſinuate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the injudicious, unſtable, and unſettled; theſe (how much ſoever they may humour and pleaſe them.) Are in truth the Perſons that offend them, that is, that withdraw them from their Duty, and Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion them to Sin. For,</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath upon no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given Occaſion of Offence to any, ſhe hath not done any thing that may Diſcourage any Honeſt Man in the way of his Salvation. But hath uſed all means to ſet up the Kingdom of Chriſt, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Intereſt of Souls. Her Doctrines are the ſame with the Goſpel, and the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints, ſhe hath preſerved pure, and deliver'd uncorrupted to her Children. And thoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102605:13"/>who are offended at theſe, would likewiſe be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at Chriſt, if he was alive. But this I ſhall not now need to inſiſt upon, it being not denyed by any, except the wildeſt ſort of Separatiſts. But doth ſhe not give Milk with one Breaſt, and Poyſon with the other? tho' her Doctrines be pure, yet the Liturgy and Ceremonies ſhe impoſes may pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and defile our Conſciences. And this might be ſomething, if our Ceremonies were Numerous and Cumberſome, if they were a Clog and Impediment to Piety and Devotion, if they were invented, and ſet up by our Church, and not uſed by the beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in Ancient Times; But if they are, for their number, few; for their Nature, fit and apt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Religion and God's Worſhip: If they have been uſed by the Primitive and early Chriſtians, then they cannot in Reaſon offend: And why ſhould the Common Prayer, and the Sign of the Croſs corrupt us, which did very well agree, with the Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the beſt and pureſt Chriſtians? But that which I ſhall chiefly inſiſt on, is comprehened in theſe three Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Methods the Church proceeded with in theſe Things upon the Reformation, ſeem'd moſt proper to revent Offences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Things ſhe hath retain'd are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and Uſeful, apt to advance Religion and Gods Worſhip, and to ſecure it from Irreverence and Profanation, and therefore might reaſonably be enjoyn'd for the benefit of a Religious Society, tho ſome Perſons of that Society might miſtake them, or not approve them</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102605:14"/>
            <p n="3">3. That ſhe hath taken all poſſible Care to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ev'n the moſt Scrupulous, of her Innocency, and the cleerneſs of her Intentions in impoſing them, and ſo hath uſed all reaſonable ways to take off Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Offences, and hath in all things (as much as the thing would admit) condeſcended to the weakeſt, and moſt infirm in Faith, or Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>And theſe three being made out, it will appear, that the Church is ſo far from being Occaſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the Weak, that ſhe hath exerciſed all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lenity and Tenderneſs towards them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Methods the Church proceeded with in theſe things upon the Reformation, ſeemed moſt proper to prevent Offences, and that was when ſhe excluded all things that were Novel, Sinful, and tireſome, and retain'd what was of undoubted An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, eaſie, and uſeful. And this, (whatſoever ſome hot Men may think) was certainly the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt courſe that could be taken to prevent Offences on all Hands. Had there been more, and more trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome kept, thoſe that complain now, might have Reaſon to be offended? Had all been thrown away, as well the uſeful as others, a contrary Party might have been offended, and when they ſaw us reform from what was convenient, they might have eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the whole Reformation not juſt and neceſſary, but peeviſh or politick, and carry'd on for other ends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides REligion and the Salvation of Souls. I know this kind of reaſoning will not down with ſome, and a man ſhall hardly eſcape from being call'd a Papiſt for urging it. But for all that, ſince 'tis neceſſary the Church ſhould open its Arms to receive all, ſince the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102605:14"/>Apoſtle enjoyns, to give no offence, neither to the <hi>Jew,</hi> nor to the <hi>Gentile;</hi> it was (eſpecially at that time when a Nation was to be converted from the dregs of <hi>Popery</hi>) not only the Wiſdom, and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but the Chriſtianity too of the firſt Reformers to carry things with ſo much evenneſs and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency; as not to pleaſe the Fury and Heats of the one Hand, nor the Errors and Faults on the other: And this took away a great many Offences, which were and ſtill are objected againſt Reformations in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places. And when they ſaw that we did not throw away the Mettle with the Droſs, that we did not caſt off things profitable with the unprofitable, it was a plain Evidence, that the end of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was Truth, not Deſign; that what was aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at was not Oppoſition, Contradiction, or Intereſt, but only to eſtabliſh and ſet up the Purity of the Goſpel. And this juſt and equal Dealing, was the moſt prudent and Conſcientious courſe that could be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to prevent offences, and a great many were by this means brought into the Church (for moſt of the Nation was converted) who in all probability, by other Furious Methods, by cutting up Root and Branch (as they call it) by deſtroying every thing then in uſe, how uſeful ſoever, would have been off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ended, that is, they would have been diſcouraged, and rather have kept to their old ſuperſtitions, than have entred into a Church which Acted ſo Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably.</p>
            <p>I know it is ſaid, that this Method was proper e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in the Infant ſtate of Reformation when mens minds were yet hankering after Ceremonies and they could not ſo ſoon be wean'd from their old Dotages,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102605:15"/>and therefore it might then be neceſſary to comply with them, for fear of diving them quite away from us. But it is not ſo now, a thorow Reformation would be more fit and ſuitable; men are now grown more wiſe and underſtanding, and know that theſe things are vain and empty, Superſtitous and Ridiculous, and therefore Iaffirm,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The things retain'd are decent and uſeful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There are but Three or Four things about which all this ſtir is made, as the Surpliſs, and Liturgy, the Croſs in Baptiſm, and Kneeling at the Communion: Each of which notwithſtanding is fit and proper. Let any unprejudic'd man conſider, whether a Decent and Solemn way of Worſhip is not apt to impreſs Reverence on mens minds, and whether diſtinction of Habits do's not contribute to the Solemnity. It plainly does ſo in Magiſtrates and Judges, and no Mortal man can give a Reaſon, why it ſhould not have the ſame influence in Religious as well as Civil things. Is not Gods worſhip like to be better ſecur'd from indecency, miſtake and miſcarriage, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Rules, than by leaving the Modes to every giddy mans fancy and opinion? Is not a form of words, where the matter is maturely thought on, and every expreſſion well weigh'd, more fit to excite Devotion, more ſuitable to expreſs the peoples wants and deſires, than raſh, inconſiderate, and haſty thoughts, than idle, intemperate, and ridiculous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions? Is not the Croſs, the Badg of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion? And when we are Baptiz'd into Chriſt's Death, is it not fit we ſhould be minded of it? That we now take up the Croſs, and are to be Crucify'd to the World, that we ſhould not be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102605:15"/>aſham'd of a Crucify'd Saviour, but own and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his Religion in ſpight of all oppoſition. When Men worſhip God, and Commemorate infinite bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, is it not fit this ſhould be done in the humbleſt poſture? That therefore when we praiſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn thanks to God and our Saviour, and are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his Body and Blood, we rather Kneel, then behave ourſelves as his equals, or as if we had been at a bodily entertainment with one of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are plain and obvious at the firſt ſight, as very proper and expedient for the more or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and comely carrying on of Gods Worſhip. And this is the firſt thing to be inquir'd into as to the impoſition of any thing, whether they are fit for the purpoſes they are intended, and if they are, then there is ſufficient Reaſon for the commanding them, tho ſome Perſons ſhould not like them, or ſhould fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to inconvenience by them, and the Reaſon is becauſe the end of Laws is the good of the Society, and if the good of the greateſt part is thereby promoted, it juſtifies and warrants ſuch Impoſitions: Now the Power the Church is inveſted with is for Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and if it injoyns ſuch things as are apt to edifie, if it belongs to her to look after Gods ſervice, and if what ſhe hath ordain'd tends to the more due and Solemn performance of the things of Religion, to make men, at their Worſhip Reverent and Devout, and to prevent them from being vain, light, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, then there is great Reaſon for the impoſing theſe things, tho ſome Perſons ſhould be offended at them; there could never any Laws be made, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Mans diſlikes or offences were to be firſt conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102605:16"/>the beſt things will offend ſome, <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith. <hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bonae res neminem ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant niſi malam mentem. Tertul. de veland. virginib.</note> Good things offend none but the Evil,</hi> Humility and Charity offend the proud and the covetous, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Peace are not agreeable to the turbulent and factious. Neither will be Laws enjoyning Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Order, and Uniformity be pleaſing to them, who love Diſtraction, Solvenlineſs, and Irreverence in Gods Worſhip.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Church hath taken all poſible care to give all Satisfaction of Innocence and clearneſs in her injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and ſo hath done (what lay in her) to take off all unreaſonable prejudices and offences againſt them. If ſome have taken miſtakes and miſapprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, if ſhe hath taken all care to rectifie thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, if they will ſtill be offended, the Church is by no means chargeable with thoſe offences, ſhe hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo much pains to remove. And herein the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Condeſcention of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is very Remarkable; there is not one of thoſe things which have been objected againſt her, but have been anſwered with all poſſible Clearneſs and Satisfaction, and there hath been all care taken fully to inform them of the clearneſs of her intentions, for inſtance, ſhe hath declar'd over and over, that ſhe places no Holineſs in Veſtments, nor in any other Ceremonies, only ſhe uſeth them for Decency, Edification, and out of a due reſpect to Antiquity. That the Croſs in Baptiſm is not a new Sacrament, that it is not, nor ever was intended by her as any addition to Chriſts inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but only as a convenient initiating Rite into the Church. That by enjoyning Kneeling at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſhe doth not intend any adoration of the Bread and Wine, but only a ſuitable geſture for the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102605:16"/>purpoſes we are about at the Sacrament. And the like may be ſaid of every other thing that is cavill'd at. And now if after theſe full and often Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they are reſolv'd they will not believe them, nor examine the Truth of them; if they are ſtill reſolv'd to be miſtaken, their miſtakes are Obſtinate and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and it is not in the Churches power to help it, ſhe hath done all ſhe can do, they may, if they will be ſtill offended and fly from our Communion, but ſurely it can never with any Reaſon be ſaid, the Church hath occaſioned them ſo to do. And this is the Fifth thing.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I ſhall endeavour, briefly to apply this to our Practiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us with Zeal and Vigor aſſert the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Church notwithſtanding the miſtakes, or pretended offences of ignorant or ill meaning Men. I would not be ſo miſtaken, as if I had not all the Charity for every honeſt man, tho he is miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: But ſurely it does not become us to feed their miſtakes, and for want of acquainting them with their Duty, to ſuffer them to continue in error all their lives long; the more Charity we have for them, the greater care we ſhall take to inſtruct them, and to win them from the Error of their ways. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are Mealy Mouth'd, or (which is worſe) when by any unworthy complyances we yeild to them, or connive at them, we humour their Errors and really offend them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us be careful of our Converſation that as the Church hath not, ſo we may give no occaſion of offence. Innocent Ceremonies are not, but ill lives are offenſive, vice was always Scandalous; and if this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102605:17"/>way we pervert any, we are reſponſible for the offences we cauſe. Our Follies will reflect upon the Church; thoſe who never examin'd it's principles, will be apt to think her as vitious, as our ſelves, that ſhe connives at thoſe Crimes her Members commit. I know 'tis not reaſonable from the Sins of Profeſſors to argue evil of the Religion: But ſince the whole World is Govern'd more by Example, then direction, it will certainly concern us, for the Churches ſake, and for our own, that we do not juſtly occaſion men to ſpeak evil of her, or of us. There is not a vice the Church of <hi>England</hi> tolerates, nor a vertue that it doth not encourage to, and yet (we may remember) the irregularities of ſome particular Members was made an objection againſt the whole Church, every Error, or Looſeneſs in a Member was made the fault of the Church. And ſo it is ſtill, our Mother will be wounded through our ſides, every diſorder we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit will be an Arugment againſt her, and a diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement from her Communion; we may Reaſon for ever; but if we do not live too, we ſhall never gain Men to our Church; Reaſon is an abſtruſe thing and all have not Faculties; but bad manners are obvious, and every man hath talent enough to know; our Sins therefore will hinder more then our perſwaſions can draw, and thoſe that can never anſwer our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, will yet gain Ground by our Vices; and here truely we are beholding to our Adverſaries, they will be ſure to mind us of our Faults and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when there is no Ground, and think by charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to diſcharge themſelves even from far greater Sins: But our faults will not make them Innocent, and an Irregular behaviour in a Church-Member
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102605:17"/>will not juſtifie <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Faction,</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> in a Seperatiſt. Nor yet will their diſorders acquit ours, nor will ours be leſs becauſe theirs are greater. What I ſhall therefore recommend is, that whereas they cannot ſpeak againſt us as <hi>Rebels, Schiſmatics, Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Turbulent,</hi> and <hi>unquiet,</hi> we may take care they ſhall not juſtly charge us with any other vice: For let us do what we can, they will ſpeak evil of us, which we cannot help, but we can help, and let us take care, that they do not do it juſtly, but as the Apoſtle ſaith, (1 Pet. 2.12.) <hi>Let us have our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation Honeſt among them, that whereas they ſpeak againſt us as evil-doers, they may be our good Works, which they ſhall behold glorify God in the Day of Viſitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
